software engineering radio episode 72
Eric Mayer on link
[Music]
hi everybody welcome to another episode
of software engineering radio this is
our no on the microphone and today I'm
talking to Eric mayor about link
language embedded queries and this is
also part of the oops la port cast in
preparation for the oops la where eric
is going to give it talk about over link
as well so Eric how about you just will
just start by you giving our listeners
some background about yourself who are
you what are your areas of interest what
will you do obviously Eric Myers and you
know I think since the first time wrong
up my friends in high school tried to
explain to me you know that x equals x
plus wrong in trs-80 basic you know
didn't mean you know x equals x plus
wrong but that sort of sounds like
you're working for Microsoft okay um so
you're you're sort of you brainchild the
thing you're working curve working on
right now is is link I heard about that
I mean that's why we're talking here
what is link what is what is it about
appreciation of language integrated
query
is to enable kind of easy
clearing and manipulation of kind of in
old forms of data in you know any dotnet
language the way we achieve that is by
importing ideas from functional
programming in particular monads and
Monette comprehensions to kind of unify
all the different data models so you
know often people kind of you know
emphasize the differences between data
most know like xml sequel of X and so
they say you know they are all very
different but the trick is that if you
all view them with youryour monadic you
know glasses on they are really similar
and that kind of allows us to define one
clear language that you can use to query
over these different data models that
sounds really great um could you tell us
a little more about what these common
abstractions are how you actually go
about collections are very similar and
if you define a set of operators that
can say filter and apply a function to
each element of a collection
and you know Schwartz collections group
the elements into scanning of partitions
all these kind of operations are really
you can't define them independently of
the specific collection content and it's
nothing more than using interface based
programming so we define you know in a
specific interface and that all these
different kind of collections implement
and then the queries are defined in
terms of that interface and so really
you know you can view it you know they
all were you told complicated
mathematics the other hand you can say
we're just using common sense
object-oriented principles you know you
define an interface only starts
implemented interface and then you can
define your functionality underlying
implementation yeah that sort of makes
sense but well I'm I'm playing devil's
advocate a little um there are certain
differences between let's say XML and
sequel XML is hierarchically structured
sequel is sort of a global data pool
that you just query where you can start
at any point and sort of just follow the
relations in how do you you know I don't
know say a three is no point or three
and in relational data it's around right
you know if I have customers in order
ste or their swords to the customer to
which they belong and the relationships
are kind of outside in
however you know if you you can let
these kind of relationships the external
relationships to internal relationships
and this is what the kind of our mapping
frameworks do for you so you kind of
bridge that gap by specifying you know
how a table apps to a certain class and
how this relationship that in the
database goes the other way around it's
not to kind of a property or education
that goes from there kind of you know
the source through the kind of target
and that was a very good question now if
we're going to speculate a little bit
and some of the things that I think it's
very interesting this extent
object-oriented languages with this
notion of external or explicit
relationships and there's you know a
fair number of research where people
have been kind of you know floating
several ideas on how to do that sort of
sort of sort of treating the objects is
a global pool that can be treated
globally using a starting point that
sort of outside them and using
relationships that are sort of not part
of the objects to to relate them to each
other is that what you're talking about
yes you know the powerful thing that you
get there is that you don't have to
define these relationships from so in
the relational database you know you can
define a relationship with a link table
in the middle so that means that you
don't have to change the price that you
relate and I think that's very powerful
because in objects you have to know you
know that you want to relate to times
and especially if you think about you
know and like the departments where you
don't have control over the types that
you want to relate having this kind of
notion of external relations is very
powerful and but again as I said you
know in most of our mapping frame
works you gonna define your classes and
you've got to bake in these kind of
relationships and classes through these
collections of tables but but they're
you know you lose some of the power of
the relational model and I'll admit that
right away so that's kind of something I
want to bring into the object-oriented
languages okay but in awhile in in in a
relational database you have this kind
of notion of a foreign keys or joins how
do you generalize that to let's say XML
okay so it's really you know warranty
and what is you know a join so ot is
it's just that make sense for kind of
any anything that had some form of
identity right because from the outside
I just have to identify the thing that I
want to point to and so and and and
again for XML you might use the fact
that maybe you know each each node in
the XML must have some kind of identity
or you can you know if the document has
identity you can use a combination of
the document identity and some part and
then you know join this in some sense
Wow
you know in the most naive way it's the
kind of a nested loop where you're kind
of checking some condition and of course
we all know how to kind of you know make
that more efficient using MVC s or link
tables so the implementation of that
Association will use all the kind of you
know tricks that the relational database
people have developed so the language
integrated career is sort of based on
this notion of having a global pool of
data and then probably this is what you
were talking about call it code filters
you sort of filter all data by by a
query by a condition let's say the the
a dress number is the ID of something
else that kind of thing is is that sort
of breaking it down to the concrete
levels that what you're talking about
you have to keep in mind that that
linkage job doesn't address this yet so
link what link gives you is a kind of
query syntax you know in the language
that is different in terms certain set
of predefined operators and now when
you're when you're playing relational
data these queries are translated into
secret that will do the join okay so
that that kind of works what I've been
well I was speculating about right now
is can we lift this notion of you know
at foreign keys and external
relationship into the programming
language and so it's kind of orthogonal
searcher the language integrated query
gives you the syntax and operators for
doing these kind of queries the next
step is to add the infrastructure the
runtime infrastructure to do you know
official joins in memory mm-hmm I see
yeah but before we get to that there are
certain well-established languages for
querying I mean select statements as
part of the sequel standard or XPath for
computing XML is linked at a higher
level of abstraction in what ways does
it go beyond these I mean I could well
you easily imagine sort of generalizing
sequel to be executable on XML data as
well
so in what ways does link go beyond
these the kind of thing exactly what
well I try to explain before so when you
you know they have and has a very
different language so how can be
generalized obese very language or this
common all these very languages such
that we can have one uniform career
language that can vary all the different
paper yeah that'd really be cool but I
still don't understand when what ways
link goes beyond let's say sequel it
should be possible to write aims let's
say cross compiler from cross translator
whatever from sequel to XPath so you
could probably execute check check the
selected subset of sequel and apply that
to all kinds of different data sources
in what ways does does link go beyond
that or is link just another syntax for
things that
you know one language engine pilot or
copilot into the other and I like to
program in C sharp or VV and I don't you
know I don't want to write sequel I want
to write this in terms of you know the
language that I know and in terms of
these or in terms of objects that I
don't that I know and then you know
these queries gets compiled equal okay
so those are the strengths and the way
in which link goes beyond circular XPath
is that is integrated with the with the
language with the object and type model
of the language in which it is
integrated yeah that's an interesting
point why don't you just tell us a
little more about in what way link is
actually integrated with the language
with the type system of the language an
implementation of this kind of common
interface of these these operators is
what we call the standard clear
operators and now in c-sharp you can
just write a query in query syntax that
syntax is some kind of combination or a
mixture of sequel and you know sequel
select where group by and xquery kind of
flower expressions the compar and the
compiler then translates these queries
into the underlying operators and but it
means that you know the the object model
that your program against are just does
not object so you're talking in terms of
you know customers and orders and their
strings and integers and so on and then
depending on the implementation of
operators you know that can take death
query and then compile it to sequel you
know run it on sequel server get back a
without the WL result and kind of you
know surface these things as as object
and another implementation that we have
is an XML done and now you know you can
query over over that so because you know
you can ask given the children of this
node it just gives you a collection and
then you can use all the queries that
work over ordinary collections and on
that but you you can easily imagine that
you could take this query and you know
compile it to you know whatever target
language you have you know whatever
native query engine that you have that
your your data model kind of you know
supports and then methods you know into
objects similar to kind of you know the
link to seek or link to entities okay so
the the the integration means that the
output of the query is sort of types of
the language or object of the language
and that it sort of navigate using the
at yeah the abstractions using the
references and whatever of the language
into which you are embedded right now
yes so yeah so but you can do and then
let me kind of go back to that later sir
yes sir so we usually the normal cases
that you use normal you have you have
some object that you know is mapped from
you know the underlying data type and
then you just use property or field
navigation to kind of move between them
but one of the things that we also have
is reactive special operators in the
query language for doing joints so if
you want to do is join you know we have
queries that can do joints and that's
you know that are implemented
efficiently or can be translated into
sequel joints so even if you want to
- you know the more relational kind of
you know relationship navigation you can
also express that using a query so you
don't see a customer's orders but you
say you know from customers from from
see and customers you know join Oh in
orders um you know some expression you
know that relates to the foreign and
primary key and so we allow both kind of
forms of navigation okay I see so I'm
beginning to get the picture how it is
sort of as a generalization and the
integration with the languages that adds
the value is there any support in in
link for writing data or changing
modifying data in any way because
thinking I think of the overall life
cycle of data careering is by far the
most complex thing but if I sort of
define this this URI these relations
between my type system and the
underlying data it would be nice to use
that and then for links to sequel and
link to entities we do support chain
stressing so you know if you if you
bring in objects from the database and
you modify them in memory we track the
change and then you can submit the
changes back and again this is something
that most of our frameworks have and
what we don't have yet is a book update
your like sequel where you can do you
know
kind of relatively easy to adversity we
just didn't get around to doing that Joe
and but there's nothing that prevents
you from doing that yeah I mean that's
that's one area where many of the Oh
army PES have the weaknesses as well so
yeah it's easy to see how it can be
generalized but that's I don't think
that's a big issue because I mean if you
want to sort of do bulk things you tend
to want to optimize in some other way so
we have also support for you know you
can do all these things we are stored
procedures so if you have a stored
procedure for doing these things and you
can do you know call the store teachers
an interesting thing that we also have
and because we have been talking about
like you know relationship navigation
quite a bit is that you can specify
using a stored procedure to navigate the
relationships you don't have to go via
join so maybe you know your DBA and has
you know some stored procedure that
given you know a customer gifts it's old
or short yeah then you can use that and
our framework you say you know whenever
you say customers those orders you know
use that stored procedure instead of
kind of you know generating sequel okay
I see um but do you have a sort of
common abstraction for modifications of
data or is that specific for the
different mappings so and the the way
you kind of modify data that is
dependent on the kind of you know T the
object context API right so you know
that that is where the change tracking
of course so we have like instance based
you know updates and so on so that's
kind of specific and really to the you
know the the the object that you're the
abstraction of the database
I will tell you know and not so much on
the town of query mechanism okay I see
that
that makes sense mmm
in what ways what freedom do you have to
specify the mapping between the data
model and your object model that returns
the results I mean it's simple if they
if the fields the the classes I'll have
the same name as let's say the the xml
elements and the fields in the class
have the same names as the but you know
that's kind of that allows you to do
more with your mappings but again you
know I think the design space there is
enormous on how to specify that yeah
that's that's definitely so is there
is there specific syntax for that or is
it an API how is linked sort of
structured internally is it is it sort
of like a language I mean we're talking
about different mappings that sort some
sort of sounds like there is an API
abstraction where you sort of plug in so
what's the architecture of link so again
you have to kind of you know make a
distinction between lengths the kind of
core language is the the the sequence
operators lost the clear syntax and then
the specifics kind of you know the eyes
interface or the mobile and it's usually
kind of nothing it's kind of specific to
that API or to that data model and that
can clear up later but usually the kind
of the way the mapping is done I mean
that I think most most of our frameworks
use something similar like you know
again it ranges from just employing this
thing from the bags or in custom
attributes or in Jonathan's annotations
on the glasses or having some kind of
external XML file that specifies that
nothing it's in some sense orthogonal to
to kind of the core of link yeah but so
is from the perspective link is the
mapping just an API the disorder of need
to provide an implementation for or is
there a sort of default syntax to
provide the mapping link you
in c-sharp on TV additional particular
Korean syntax and and it specifies this
set of standard operators that you know
that is the target of these frameworks
that use these queries and the
expression 3 generated by these queries
to interface with you know an external
database or an external data source and
it's these api's that kind of you know
where this mapping is specified and
because that's where you know that's the
kind of boundary between the object
world and the the external data model
world so this whole issue of mapping
sort of outside the link core and it's
up to the providers of the plugins for
the specific data implementations yes I
think it's the beauty of link is that
that that is really in some sense a very
general framework in language we do this
to your API you know we have we can have
the representation of those queries and
then you know you do whatever you want
with it and you know that's probably
paralyzed by so nothing that you've got
of you you do whatever you want with and
so so that's the kind of power right is
not scanning that is not hardwired it's
really kind of a general-purpose
framework for for doing for do for
dealing with data and with old forms of
data so that that's the nice thing about
it I think then we're not tied down to
you know XML or sequel and some party
alarm mapping format one of the things
that is sort of hard to implement when
you're right in Oh our mapper and is
really powerful when you use a network
our mapper is lazy loading with all the
different kinds of optimizations for
prefetching and that kind of thing is
there any support for that link or is um
it sounds like let's probably up to the
to the implementation of the of the
actual data format plug-in as well is
this is like that
exactly so and let me give you a
specific example of that so for example
link to seek law allows eater and lazy
loading and you know that is again you
know that's something that specified he
said exactly body by the link to sequel
a plan and that's kind of takes care of
that and when you write a query you know
working ego ego this early reloaded
relationship in a different way it is
you know the underlying infrastructure
that takes care of that and then again
that's well then you know make sure has
made sure that you know all the stuff
gets implemented efficiently
what mappings does link come with I mean
if you use Visual Studio what mappings
do you get out of the box without having
to know
you know which is the model you will see
that people are doing all kind of
interesting with some external data
source okay so let's let's say I want to
start a link project
what sort of roads should I plan for for
um for people to sort of interact with
link and how should I go about
integrating link into a let's say large
application for that's a large banking
application wherever people sort of well
the teller and enters data and go back
to the beta base the usual thing how
would it go about integrating or what
what role should I plan for what needs
to be done you know and maybe I think
here probably during the last Enterprise
there will be some kind of usually
people have already kind of some kind of
our framework there so in I think that's
the kind of more interesting case in
some sense in which case you have to
kind of implement your own so okay so
let's let's say I sort of heavy
relational database but
there are some specifics that go beyond
what is there out of the box you know
you want to take something out of the
box linkage equal and you know what you
would do is there are several tools you
know there's kind of you know designer
tools where you could where you import
your database and you kind of define
your the mapping between your tables and
your glasses and you know once you have
done that and now you can and so maybe
as I said you know maybe your your
database user stored procedures and
again you know the tools and the
framework allows you to kind of you know
find sort procedures to you know to this
query so I can you know to use stored
procedures to navigate a certain
relationship you specify which things
are loaded lazily orderly and then once
you have done that so it's just a matter
of writing C sharp or visual basic code
using these queries and and sometimes
that's actually very much the same if
you would use like you know linked to
entities you know there you know you
would specify the mapping between your
database and your object and you know
from their own you just write very
sincere sharp or VB these queries you
know the result of that query is some
piece of sequel that gets executed on
the server and the results come back and
then they are materialized as objects so
it's the nice
let's say if we compare it to the way
they say you know thing cassettes or
something like that they're you you
would have to you know writes sequel as
strengths that you pass through an API
right so you would kind of you know open
the connection and then you have to
write it create a sequel commands that
you do by you know putting some sequel
string and that you pass through the API
then you get back the results as you
know kind of untyped tables and so
you're not a you're not programming in
terms of you know your your objects and
plus that you don't get any kind of you
know intelligence or checking of the
actual query and this is the the big
advantage is that when you you know when
you link your your queries are
statically typed you get for
intelligence and type checking such that
you know you never try to you know I
don't know I see so that's the the
integration part again enhanced with IDE
support and the aesthetic static typing
how to what degree would you say does
link scale sorts of let's say huge
applications of thousands of classes
tens of thousands of classes and when I
was talking about scalability I mean
maintainability for large for large
projects um it's it sounds like a great
way to get started quickly to get first
results very easily very quickly and
it's easy for me to believe that it's
great at that do you have any experience
or any sort of estimate for for large
applications or is it more targeted at
the small and simple applications
we kind of tried to answer this question
you know without sounding you know fake
so there there is an interesting you
know if you look on the web one of the
performance architects in this block you
know stuff about the performance of link
to sequel and the thing is that if you
compare it to say you have to write the
complex query by hand right so you're
using just old-fashioned data set or you
know a double net and you have to write
a complicated query and that involves
joins and whatever and the tenses that
you know you like by hand it's done you
know I think you know letting the
compiler do that it's usually a better
bet but on the other hand you know if if
you if you encapsulate that query using
a stored procedure say you know there's
some specialist that really knows how to
write this optimal serve you can use it
to all we even allow you to kind of you
know if that's what you want to still
kind of - the whole thing and and and
and you sequel directly so the thing is
that I think intrinsically you're not in
some sense anything you could do before
you can still do and and we're trying to
make it easier to do what you did before
but you know so let me answer the
question like this if you could write
you know your applications before using
you know that's and
and they just enter on or data reader
you get that's you know those
applications will still work I cannot
the enemy no say in general it's like
there's no we're not taking anything
away so to speak so there's nothing
intrinsically there that you know stands
in your way it's just kind of taking
away the noise that you would have to
deal with you know writing sequel
queries by hand
okay I see yeah I was sort of looking at
from it from different perspective
compared to let's same full-blown our
mappers like in hibernate or something
that have sort of evolved over years
have been used for huge projects and
sort of our targeted at maintainability
and sort of more specialized the less
general but well I would expect it to be
easier to write a full-blown so our
mapper that is a little better at our
mapping then the link approach the
resort
generalizes the data model so you know
okay so yeah yeah that makes sense so
sort of beside the beside the point
because the link is sort of a the query
interface that can be plugged on top of
an arbitrary or our memory I see that
exactly and what I like so much about it
right because there will be you know
imagine that at some point and I don't
know and
you come out with your own kind of you
know special you know whatever you want
to be able to kind of prairie that from
a nice way from P B and C sharp so
that's you know that's the kind of thing
that that's supported by the language
all languages and and the kind of
standard library and then we allow you
to okay yeah I think I got the idea so I
think I sort of got the the big picture
got the overview of Linc
would you like to add anything is
anything you use do you think that
should be added talking about Lincoln
anything we missed so far so yes also
one of the things that's kind of
interesting and when we talks about like
a relational data in the beginning one
of the interesting things is if you look
in relational relational data is kind of
flat right it's never nested so for
example that means that in sequel
whenever you do an aggregation again and
then you know operators and for instance
you know if you want to have a hierarchy
often get to do you know if you want to
return the higher to research you have
to do two queries right and then you
know
after reconstructive hierarchy you know
on the way back all of these things are
pretty hard to rely on the compiler
typically expressions and clouds embassy
call and all these things become and and
I think that is one of the to me one of
the nice things of having this kind of
you know more abstract data model that's
kind of your generalizes each of these
is that it it's kind of very
compositional you can think you know you
can break up your queries in little
pieces and understand them kind of you
know oh by themselves and then kind of
hook them up together
and whereas often in inch equal you know
you have to have this query that's kind
of you know there's no kind of
monolithic very right that they say from
select group why that's yeah especially
combined with these with the support in
the IDE that's certainly a very very
beautiful
that's true and the other things that I
think you know one thing that we haven't
really discussed a bit which is I think
very very cool it's the notion of
expression three so and I kind of
mentioned this between the lines a
couple of times right in which the
queries are designed and one of the
implementation of that takes you know
expression trees that represent
delegates that represents ear you you
know you're doing a float or a war now
you pass at that base you know the first
educate very gate as an expression three
so it's a the kind of abstract syntax
tree that represents that delegate and
kind of a method programming ability so
instead of having you know representing
your board on a strange often you know
as I said like you know
sequel API server you thought this
equals three registering or a lot of
excellent advice to write the XPath
expressions as strings and now you know
you the compiler will ensure all the
stuff you create these expression trees
and then so this is a much higher level
of abstraction than than this
unstructured string and I think you know
there's a lot of opportunity to use
these expression trees outside
in particular I mean we talked a lot
about you know and like an apprehension
but imagine you know there's interesting
research in Microsoft Research here that
uses you know your GPU which is like a
parallel you know take a parallel
machine and what you can do is you can
now take some computation over you know
some kind of array of floating point
numbers or something expressed in length
and instead of comparing it to sequel
you compile it to the instructions of
your GPU you know in your graphics cards
[Laughter]
so again that's why you know it's like a
really link is a very very general
mechanism this in some senses it's
independent of relational data area so
you can use it to to run on your GPU and
thank you like f sharp don't sign as a
very nice example of doing that you know
in F sharp where he uses the link
expression 3 you're gonna do that and as
I said you know I think this is just a
tip of the iceberg when people start to
discover this kind of meta programming
and and this has been of course you know
existed in Lisp and scheme for for ages
right for 50 years I don't know how long
but now this position these kind of
mainstream languages and and you know
once people start to discover that I
think you know interesting things can
happen so I just want to stretch that
link you know it's really this general
framework
for expressing queries based on some
kind of common interface and then you
know it's everybody can can provide an
implementation of these operators and
that may have nothing to do with
relational data mm-hmm yes
well thank you very much all right nice
talking to you
quite interesting I think we have a lot
better understanding about how to query
data now thank you very much and see you
it looks love
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineer a do
website for details